Guide to the Andrew Alpern Papers circa 1920-2015 PR 324
New-York Historical Society
Andrew Alpern papers
circa 1920-2015 (bulk, 1980-2000)
New-York Historical Society
Alpern, Andrew
PR 324
27 Linear feet (27 record cartons)
This collection consists of the reference files and reports authored and/or maintained by New York architect, historian and attorney Andrew Alpern. The files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings. Included are reference files for Alpern's 2001 book The New York Apartment Houses of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter as well as his 2015 book The Dakota: A History of the World's Best Known Apartment Building. The collection also includes reports related to New York City landmark designation cases prepared by Andrew Alpern.
Acquisition Note
Gift of Andrew Alpern, 2015, 2016, 2018.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
The videotapes and CDs are restricted because of their fragility and because N-YHS has no equipment on which to play them.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection is made up of the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern.
Series I is focused on specific New York City buildings and neighborhoods. These files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings.
Series II contains the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern for the book The New York Apartments of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter. The files include images, articles, newspaper clippings, promotional materials and correspondence related to the book.
Series III consists of copy negatives. They are mainly images of the NYC buildings featured in the reference files, identified on their outer envelopes.
Series IV consists of 62 slides of New York City buildings featured in Alpern's 1975 book Apartments for the Affluent.
Series V consists of reports related to New York City landmark designation cases. The reports were prepared by Andrew Alpern between 1987-2008.
Series VI contains reference files focused on specific New York City buildings and neighborhoods, donated in 2018. These files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings.
Series VII consists of research and reports completed by Christopher Gray (1950-2017).
Series VIII contains the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern for the 2015 book The Dakota: A History of the World's Best Known Apartment Building. The files include images, articles, newspaper clippings, promotional materials and correspondence related to the book.
This finding aid is based on the inventory written by Andrew Alpern. All descriptions and identifications were provided by Mr. Alpern. The bulk of the collection consists of reproductions (photocopies of articles, contemporary copy negatives of historical photographs, etc.). The dates of the collection reference the dates of the original material from which the copies were made.
Biographical/Historical Note
Andrew Alpern (b. 1938) is a New York architect, architectural historian, and attorney. He is the author of four books about apartment houses in New York City, including Apartments for the Affluent: A Historical Survey of Buildings in New York, (NY, McGraw-Hill, Inc., 1975) and The New York Apartment Houses of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter, (NY, Acanthus Press, 2001).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series by subject and/or format.
Series I: Building and Neighborhood Reference Files 1920-2001
Series II: Series II: Reference Files for The New York Apartments of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter
Series III: Copy Negatives
Series IV: Slides
Series V: Reports related to NYC landmark designation cases, 1987-2008
Series VI: 2018 Accrual - Reports/Research Files 1920-2015
Series VII: 2018 Accrual - Reports by Christopher Gray 1977-2009
Series VIII: 2018 Accrual - Reference Files for The Dakota: A History of the World's Best Known Apartment Building
Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Photographs.; building history research; Gray, Christopher, 1950-2017
- Series I: Building and Neighborhood Reference Files, 1920-2001
  General Note
  This series is made up of the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern, focused on specific New York City buildings and neighborhoods. The files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings.
  - Abigail Adams House (421 East 61st Street, Mount Vernon Hotel Museum) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amiable Child grave (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Armories (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art Deco (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Banks (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Battery Park (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Battery Park City (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Beekman Place (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Broadway (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bronx (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-10.5)
  - Brooklyn (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Brooklyn Bridge (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Bridges (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Campanile (450 East 52nd Street) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carnegie Hill (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Castle Village (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Central Park (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Chrysler Building (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Churches (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Clubs (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - Coney Island (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cooper Hewitt (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cooper Union (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Courthouses (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dodge Mansion (800 Fifth Avenue) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Empire State Building (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fifth Avenue Association (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Firefighting (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Forty-second (42nd) Street (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fraunces Tavern (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fred F. French Co. (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - General Theological Seminary (20th Street & 9th Avenue) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grand Central Terminal (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Grant's Tomb (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Andrew Haswell Green (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Greenwich Village (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Hall of Fame (Bronx) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Harlem (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hotel Endicott (Columbus Avenue & 81st Street) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hotel Pennsylvania (Seventh Avenue & 32nd Street) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Hotels (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12-16)
  - Henry Miller's Theatre (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hudson View Gardens (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ada Louise Huxtable (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
  - Inwood (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jackson Heights (Queens) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Jumel Mansion (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
  - Ladies Mile (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
  - Leonori (26 East 63rd Street) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
  - Libraries (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lower East Side (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lower Manhattan (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Lyndhurst (Tarrytown) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Madison Avenue (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Marble Hill (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Mark Cross (store) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Merchant's House Museum (Old Merchant's House, Seabury Tredwell House) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Metropolitan Museum Historic District (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Moondog (musician and "viking") (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clement C. Moore (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
  - Murray Hill (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - Museums (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - New Century Apartments (401 West End Avenue) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - Normandy (170 Riverside Drive) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pomander Walk (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
  - Queens (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
  - Restaurants (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Rhinelander (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
  - Rockefeller Center (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
  - Russell Sage Building (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
  - St. Bartholomew's Church (Park Ave & 51st Street) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
  - St. Peter's Church (West 20th Street) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
  - Schools (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - Sculpture (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sixth Avenue (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sniffen Court (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - SoHo (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Stables/Garages (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Statue of Liberty (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Steinway/Pike House (Astoria, Queens) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Stores (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Stuyvesant Square (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subways (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11-15)
  - The Sulgrave (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Sutton Place (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Synagogues (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18-20)
  - Tenement Houses (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
  - Theaters (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22-24)
  - Times Square (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Transportation (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Tudor City (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Turtle Bay (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Underground (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Union Square (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
  - Upper Manhattan (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
  - Villard Houses (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
  - Washington Heights (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
  - Waterfront (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14)
  - Westbeth (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
  - 129 East 17th Street (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - 11-17 East 45th Street (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18)
  - 160 East 72nd Street (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19)
  - 39 East 79th Street (Offsite-box 6, Folder 20)
  - 25 East 83rd Street (Offsite-box 6, Folder 21)
  - 88 Central Park West (Offsite-box 6, Folder 22)
  - 43 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 23)
  - 820 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 24)
  - 960 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 25)
  - 998 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 26)
  - 667 Madison Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 27)
  - 23 Park Avenue (Robb House) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 28)
  - 730 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 29)
  - 823 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 30)
  - 903 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 31)
  - 1185 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 32)
  - 35 Prospect Park West (Brooklyn) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 33)
  - 1213 York Avenue (Offsite-box 6, Folder 34)
- Series II: Reference Files for The New York Apartments of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter, 1925-2001
  This series is made up of the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern for the book The New York Apartments of Rosario Candela and James Carpenter, published in 2001. The files include images, articles, newspaper clippings, promotional materials and correspondence related to the book.
  - Articles (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-6)
  - Bios (other than Candela and Carpenter) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
  - Book drafts and reviews (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
  - Candela, Rosario (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
  - Carpenter, James (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
  - Floor plans (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
  - Images (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
  - Promotional materials (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
  - Research done by Christopher Gray (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
- Series III: Copy Negatives, undated
  This series is made up of copy negatives maintained by Andrew Alpern. They are mainly images of NYC buildings, identified on their outer envelopes.
  - 4 x 6 copy negatives (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16-18)
  - 8 x 10 copy negatives (Offsite-box 7, Folder 19-22)
- Series IV: Slides, 1975
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of 62 slides of New York City buildings featured in Alpern's 1975 book Apartments for the Affluent.
  - Slides from Apartments for the Affluent, 1975 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
- Series V: Reports related to NYC landmark designation cases, 1987-2008
  This series consists of reports related to New York City landmark designation cases. The reports were prepared by Andrew Alpern between 1987-2008.
  Cases involve the following properties:
  York Avenue Estates
  Coleman Station Historic District
  Tin Pan Alley Historic District
  1213 York Avenue
  Riverside Apartments, Brooklyn
  Hotel Pennsylvania
  Former Public School 64
  184 Kent Street, Austin Nichols warehouse
  Windermere Group, 400-406 West 57th Street
  55 White Street
  351-355 Central Park West
  Central Park West Historic District expansion
  - Reports, 1987 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
  - Reports, 1989-1994 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
  - Reports, 2005 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 2006-2010 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
- Series VI: 2018 Accrual - Reports/Research Files, 1920-2015
  This series is made up of the reference files maintained by Andrew Alpern, donated in 2018. The files are focused on specific New York City buildings, topics, and neighborhoods. The files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings. It also includes 2 video cassettes.
  - ABC Building, West 67th Street, 1983-1999 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
  - Gaetano Ajello, 1977-2009 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 13)
  - Albany Apartments, London (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7)
  - Alwyn Court, 182 West 58th Street (Offsite-box 19, Folder 9)
  - Ansonia, 2109 Broadway (Offsite-box 19, Folder 10-11)
  - Apartment House Names (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Apartment Houses (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1-4)
  - Apartments from Other Uses (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Apthorp Courtyards, Broadway and West 78th; and Graham Court, Seventh Avenue and West 116th Street (Offsite-box 19, Folder 3)
  - Archdiocese of New York - Souvenir Album in Commemoration of the Centennial Anniversary of the Archdiocese of New York 1808-1908 [Photocopy] (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5)
  - Architects and Builders, 1977-2007 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Austin Nichols Warehouse /184 Kent Avenue, Brooklyn, 2005 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1)
  - Belnord, 225 West 86th Street (Offsite-box 19, Folder 4)
  - Beresford, 211 Central Park West (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - C.K.G. Billings Estate, 1985-1996 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
  - Blizzard of 1888, 1888-1998 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
  - Brittania, 527 West 110th Street (Offsite-box 19, Folder 6)
  - Brownstones, 1970-2015 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 3-6)
  - Buildings - Miscellaneous (Offsite-box 23, Folder 5-8)
  - Car Barns and Bus Depots (Offsite-box 24, Folder 11)
  - Carnegie Hall, 1963-2007 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7)
    includes articles and brochures about the Carnegie Hall Studios, the live/work spaces for artists.
  - Cast Iron, 1970-2013 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8)
  - Castles, 1987-2003 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 9)
  - Cemeteries (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Central Park West (Offsite-box 23, Folder 3-4)
  - Central Park West: Building-Structure Inventory, 1975 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 2)
  - Century Apartments, 25 Central Park West (Offsite-box 19, Folder 5)
  - Chelsea (Offsite-box 22, Folder 9-10)
  - Chelsea Hotel, 222 West 23rd Street (Offsite-box 22, Folder 8)
  - Cherokee Apartments aka the Shively Sanitary Tenements, York Avenue and East 77th-78th Streets (Offsite-box 19, Folder 8)
  - Huguette Clark Residence, 907 Fifth Avenue, 1927-2013 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 10)
  - Coffee House Club, 1915-1993 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3-5)
  - Collyer Brothers (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1)
  - Columbus Avenue, 1983-2001 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
  - Bill Cunningham (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2)
  - Dorilton, 171 West 71st Street (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Duplex/Studio Buildings (Offsite-box 19, Folder 2)
  - East End Avenue, 1984-2000 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12)
  - East Side (Offsite-box 16, Folder 3)
  - El Dorado, 300 Central Park West (Offsite-box 22, Folder 7)
  - Elevators (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4)
  - Fairfax Apartment/795 Fifth Avenue, 1996-2017 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3)
  - Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 22, Folder 4-6)
  - Fifth Avenue and Central Park: Building-Structure Inventory, 1975 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4)
  - Fifty-Seventh Street (Offsite-box 21, Folder 11)
  - Jack Finney, 1983-1995 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
  - Gainsborough, 222 Central Park South (Offsite-box 18, Folder 10)
  - Harmon Hendricks Goldstone (Offsite-box 18, Folder 12)
  - Gracie Mansion (Offsite-box 16, Folder 5)
  - Gracie Square (Offsite-box 16, Folder 6)
  - Gramercy Park (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Hetty Green (Offsite-box 22, Folder 2)
  - Hampshire House, 150 Central Park South (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11)
  - George Harris, Canadian architect (Offsite-box 14, Folder 14)
  - Henrik Hudson, 380 Riverside Drive (Offsite-box 24, Folder 10)
  - Hotel des Artistes, 1 West 67th Street (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1)
  - Houses in New York City (Offsite-box 25, Folder 5-8)
  - Housing (Offsite-box 25, Folder 9)
  - The Imperial, 55 East 76th Street (Offsite-box 18, Folder 8)
  - Interiors (Offsite-box 21, Folder 12)
  - Landmarks (Offsite-box 21, Folder 3)
  - Lighting, 1981-1994 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lobbies (Offsite-box 21, Folder 5)
  - London Terrace (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
  - Majestic, 115 Central Park West (Offsite-box 17, Folder 6)
  - Manhasset, 301 West 108th Street and 300 West 109th Street (Offsite-box 17, Folder 7)
  - Montana Apartments (Offsite-box 18, Folder 5)
  - Navarro, or Spanish Flats (Offsite-box 21, Folder 4)
  - Neighborhoods (Offsite-box 21, Folder 9)
  - New York's Changing Scene newspaper feature (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6)
  - New York City history (Offsite-box 23, Folder 9)
  - Normandy, 140 Riverside Drive (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
  - Old London Street (Offsite-box 21, Folder 8)
  - Osborne, 205 West 57th Street (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-2)
  - Park Avenue (Offsite-box 24, Folder 4-5)
  - Parks (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3)
  - Penn Station (Offsite-box 24, Folder 6)
  - Penthouses (Offsite-box 24, Folder 7-8)
  - Pomander Walk, Upper West Side, 1981 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 6)
  - Prospect Park South, 1975 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate Deeds and Records, 1674, 1811-1859 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7)
  - Reform Club, 1986-1994 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
  - Renovations, 1935-2006 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
  - River House, 435 East 52nd Street, 1980-1994 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7-8)
  - Riverside Apartments, Brooklyn, 2008 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8-9)
  - Riverside Drive (Box 20, Folder 5-7)
  - Rockefeller Apartments, 1941-2015 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 9)
  - Roosevelt Island, 1975-2017 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
  - Russian Tea Room (Offsite-box 18, Folder 4)
  - St. Urban, 285 Central Park West (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
  - San Remo, 145-146 Central Park West (Offsite-box 15, Folder 11)
  - Schwab Mansion, 73rd-74th Streets, Riverside Drive to West End Avenue (Offsite-box 18, Folder 6)
  - Schwartz and Gross Architectural Firm (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Sheet Metal Company Catalogs, 1892-1909 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
  - Editta Sherman (Offsite-box 15, Folder 12)
  - Skyscrapers (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Soaring Salons - 1020 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1)
  - South Street Seaport, 1977-1989 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12-13)
  - Stairs and Escalators (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
  - Frances Steloff, Gotham Book Mart (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
  - Streets and Avenues (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3)
  - Subways, 1984-2018 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
  - Terra Cotta (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Thirty-fourth Street Reformed Church Jubilee Booklet, 1873 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 10)
  - Clarence True (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8)
  - Unbuilt Projects, 1957-2001 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
  - Verona, 32 East 64th Street (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
  - Wendel Family, Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 15, Folder 9)
  - West End Avenue, 1990-2013 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - West Side (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9-10)
  - Garret Ellis Winants, 1976 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Windermere, 400-406 West 57th Street, 1989-2005 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5-7)
  - Ida Wood (Offsite-box 22, Folder 3)
  - Woolworth Building (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
  - World War II Ration Books, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
  - Zabar Thesis: "The Influence of W. E. D. Stokes's Real Estate Career on West Side Development,", 1977 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 13)
    master's thesis by Lori Zabar [Photocopy]
  - William K. Zinsser (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
  - 351-355 Central Park West, 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
  - 605 East Ninth Street, former P.S. 64, 2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-4)
  - 45 East 66th Street - Eclectic Elegance (Offsite-box 17, Folder 2)
  - 11 East 73rd Street - Pulitzer's Modified Mansion (Offsite-box 17, Folder 5)
  - 998 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - 1010 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 17, Folder 11)
  - 1107 Fifth Avenue (Box 20, Folder 9-11)
  - 34 Gramercy Park (Offsite-box 16, Folder 9)
  - 270 Park Avenue, 2013 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
  - 417 Park Avenue - Holdout House (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1)
  - 666 Park Avenue - Magnificent Maisonette (Offsite-box 17, Folder 4)
  - 820 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1025 Park Avenue - Joyful Jacobethan (Offsite-box 16, Folder 10)
  - 1040 Park Avenue (Offsite-box 24, Folder 9)
  - 137 Riverside Drive - Hearst's Highrise (Offsite-box 17, Folder 3)
  - 44 West 77th Street - Gotham Gothic (Offsite-box 18, Folder 9)
  - 109 West Broadway/112 Reade Street, 1989 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - 300 West 72nd Street (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
  - 55 White Street, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11)
  - [Video Cassette] Andrew Haswell Green Television Coverage, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
  - [Video Cassette] Firebird Russian Restaurant, 365 West 46th Street, opening party, 1996 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
- Series VII: 2018 Accrual - Reports by Christopher Gray, 1977-2009
  This series consists of research and reports credited to New York Times columnist Christopher Gray and his Office of Metropolitan History. The files, maintained by Andrew Alpern, focus on specific New York City buildings and neighborhoods. The files primarily include photographs, articles, and newspaper clippings.
  - Adams Express Company Building, 61 Broadway, 1985 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Arnold, Constable Building, 1996 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bruce Barton House, 134 East 80th Street, 1994 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gilsey House, 1200 Broadway, 1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gorham Apartments, 891 Broadway, 1978, 2009 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Hecksher Building, 1979 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Metropolitan Club, 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Park and Tilford Building, 100 West 72nd Street, 1978 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Poughkeepsie Newspaper Building, Poughkeepsie, NY, 1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Riverdale, 67 Riverside Drive, 1978 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - John S. Rogers House, 53 East 79th Street, 1998 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Felix Rosen House, 157 East 70th Street, 1995 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - St. James Building, 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - William Schickel House, 52 East 83rd Street, 1998 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Second Church of Christ, Scientist, 1982 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Sisters of the Bon Secours Building, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
  - Stable Building, 115-119 East 75th Street, 1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
  - Townsend Building, 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
  - 467 Central Park West, 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - 220 East 51st Street, 1979 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - 14 East 53rd Street, 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - 20 East 65th Street, 1979 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - 45 East 66th Street, 1977 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
  - 230 East 68th Street, 1980 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
  - 22 East 71st Street, 1981 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)